Let's tackle the tidiness issues now,
لنعالج المشكلات المتعلقة بالترتيب الآن،
and there are a few in this dataset.
وهناك القليل في مجموعة البيانات.
Recall that this is the other way that data can be unclean.
استرجع أن هذه هي الطريقة الأخرى حيث تكون البيانات غير نظيفة.
Data can be low quality or dirty and it can be untidy or messy.
يمكن أن تكون البيانات أقل جودة أو مستهلكة ويمكن أن تكون غير منظمة أو فوضوية.
So with quality previously in this lesson,
لذلك باستخدام الجودة مسبقا في هذا الدرس،
it was issues with our data's content that we were looking for.
كانت مشاكل مع محتوى بياناتنا التي نبحث عنها.
And now with tidiness it's structural issues.
والآن مع عدم الترتيب تصبح مشاكل هيكلية.
Having tidy data makes our data easier to analyze in most cases.
الحصول على بيانات مرتبة يجعلها سهلة التحليل في معظم الحالات.
And it also makes cleaning easier as per both of these documents by Hadley Wickham,
كما أنه يجعل التنظيف أسهل لكل من هاتين الوثيقتين اللتان كتبهما هادلي ويكهام،
the creator of the tidy data format.
مخترع تنسيق البيانات المرتبة.
Regarding making data cleaning easier,
فيما يتعلق بجعل عملية تنظيف البيانات أسهل،
you'll see how this is true in the next lesson in this course which is on cleaning,
سترى كيف يتم ذلك في الدرس التالي في هذه الدورة التدريبية
the third step in the data wrangling process.
الخطوة الثالثة في عملية تبادل البيانات.
Let's go over what tidy data actually is again.
دعنا نناقش تعريف البيانات المرتبة الفعلي مرة أخرى
There are three requirements for tidiness.
هناك ثلاثة متطلبات للترتيب.
Each variable forms a column,
كل متغير يشكل عمود،
each observation forms a row,
كل ملاحظة تشكل صف،
and each type of observational unit forms a table.
وكل نوع من وحدات المراقبة يشكل جدول.
So let's start by assessing for tidiness by assessing visually directly in Pandas here.
إذا، هيا بنا نبدأ بتقييم الترتيب عن طريق التقييم البصري المباشر لمكتبة Pandas هنا.
So we've got a patients table, a treatment table,
لدينا الآن جدول لبعض المرضى، وجدول آخر به العلاج الذي يتناولونه،
and an adverse reactions table in this clinical trial data set.
وجدول ثالث يوضح الآثار الجانبية الناتجة عن تناول العلاج في مجموعة بيانات التجارب السريرية هذه.
In this patients table this contact column
في جدول المرضى يبدو عمود بيانات الاتصال هذا
is the most glaring tidiness issue in my opinion.
برأيي أهم ما يجب مناقشته.
There are two variables in one column which
يوجد متغيرين في عمود واحد
violates the "each variable forms a column" requirement.
مما يخالف متطلبات "كل متغير يمثل عمودًا".
There is phone number and also e-mail address in this contact column.
يوجد رقم هاتف وعنوان بريد إلكتروني في عمود جهة الاتصال.
These should be split into two separate columns just
يجب أن توضع بيانات هذا العمود في عمودين منفصلين
like this and that's how the record for Zoe Wellish would be filled out.
مثل هذا، وذلك يوضح كيف سجّلنا بيانات زوي ويليش.
That was done using manual cleaning which
وقد تم ذلك باستخدام التنظيف اليدوي الذي
again we shouldn't use unless it's one-off occurrences.
يجب ألا نستخدمه مرة أخرى إلا إذا كان يحدث لمرة واحدة.
And in this column it's definitely not one-off occurrences.
وفي هذا العمود من المؤكد أنه لا يحدث لمرة واحدة.
You'll write code to automate this cleaning
ستقوم بكتابة التعليمات البرمجية لأتمتة عملية التنظيف هذه
leveraging a cleaning tool called regular expressions in the next lesson.
باستخدام أداة تنظيف تسمى التعبيرات العادية في الدرس التالي.
It's a pretty amazing tool that's really flexible.
إنها أداة مدهشة للغاية ومرنة حقًا.
Okay so that's one, let's document that issue right now.
إذًا، هذه واحدة، دعنا نوثق هذه المشكلة الآن.
And once again I'd like to separate the issues by quality and tidiness when documenting.
ومرة أخرى، أرغب في فصل المعلومات المدوّنة حسب الجودة والترتيب عند التوثيق.
So we'll put this one
لذا سنضع هذا العمود
under tidiness.
قيد الترتيب.
Let's move on now.
فلننتقل إلى المرحلة التالية الآن.
Back to the visual assessment part of our Jupyter Notebook.
هيا نعُد إلى جزء التقييم البصري في Jupyter Notebook
So this treatment's table is untidy too.
جدول العلاج غير مُرتّب أيضًا.
And these Auralin and Novodra columns are the offenders.
والخلل يوجد في العمودين اللذان يحملان أسماء Auralin و Novodra
Again these have dosage information in each entry in each column.
يوضح كل من العمودين معلومات عن الجرعة في كل إدخال في كل عمود.
What tidy data rule or rules do these columns
ما هي قواعد البيانات المرتبة التي
break and how should these two columns be re-represented in a tidy format?
تفصل هذه الأعمدة، وكيف ينبغي إعادة إدخال البيانات لهذين العمودين بتنسيق مرتّب؟